[Music]
CIA
Ala CIA.
[Music]
and security forum.
Avenue
Hotel.
[Music]
Fore, how do you feel that you're in
here in Greece?
I I have I'm having trouble even putting
it into words. I said yesterday to a
friend that I'm never as happy as I am
when I'm in Greece to the point where
I've become a Greek citizen. I'm looking
for property in Athens. It makes me so
happy just to be here. So, as a Greek
American, how do you feel about your
Greek origins?
When I applied for my Greek citizenship,
I was told that because my family was
from Rodo that I had a stronger case for
Italian citizenship. I said, "I'm not
Italian. I don't want Italian
citizenship." And so it took a little
while longer, a little bit more digging,
but I got my Greek citizenship. And you
know, one of the great things about
being a Greek American is the strength
of the Greek American community. uh not
just in Washington but all over the
country, New York, Boston, Florida,
Southern California, Chicago, the Greeks
are everywhere. And we are even over
represented in Congress. We have members
of Congress that are members of the
House that are Greek Americans. Now we
have another Greek American running for
the Senate. And so, you know, we need we
need to stick together to represent
Greece's interests in the United States.
God knows that the Turkish lobby is very
strong. So it's up to the rest of us to
make sure that we protect Greece. So Mr.
Ker says used to say that the half of
CIA staff is Greek. It's true. I was
just talking uh about this to a friend
last night. When I was in the CIA, the
Greek Americans always stuck together.
We would have lunch once a month. We
would always invite the director of the
CIA, George Tennant, who's also Greek
from Ebidos and uh and this the senior
officers would always look out for the
for the junior officers, help us make
good career decisions, help us get
promoted. That has been the case since
the 1950s. Mhm. And in my own case, and
this is not necessarily a good thing,
but in my own case, my mentor at the CIA
was
Gusto, who became a legendary figure in
that he was the one who led the CIA's
efforts against the Soviet Union in
Afghanistan. Now, the reason why I say
it may not be a good thing is because he
was also a very well-known supporter of
the Ha. Yes. And uh we have some
negative memories from him because about
Cyprus. Oh yeah. Gust was a lovely man
and very proud to be Greek, but he was
obsessed with communism. Mhm. To the
point where he wasn't he didn't think
clearly. He was so obsessed with
communism and with killing communists.
Not just that he didn't like the
ideology. He he advocated the killing of
communists. Okay. But anyway, he was one
of those those Greek Americans that
wanted to make sure that young new Greek
Americans in the CIA had good careers,
made good decisions, and got promoted.
Okay. Uh, next question. How
does an agent feels after retirement?
Does does he or she feels secure? Does
she or she has the the necessity to to
be protected from the from the
government? No, that's a good question.
Uh, no. In my case, the CIA went after
me and uh because I I revealed that the
CIA was torturing its prisoners, that
torture was official policy and that the
policy had come directly from the
president. So, they they attacked me.
They sent me to prison for 2 years. I
refused to apologize. I refused to
retract anything that I said. And uh and
I still refuse because I was right and
they were wrong. But then for years
after it was all over, they followed me.
My emails were being intercepted, which
I have proof of. My phone calls were
being
monitored for what reason? But that's
just the way they they do it with with
former CIA officers who don't fit into
the mold and uh don't keep their mouth
shut. Okay, last question. You have
added her already to this. But I must
ask you that you know have an enemy a
neighbor who who is acting like an enemy
Turkey and Turkey wants to to get the
halfway.
Uh how how can face this uh this enemy?
I would say number one, do not rely on
the United States solely for your
security because you know there's an old
saying in the United States that there
are no permanent friends, only permanent
interests and it's the US's interest to
maintain good relations with Turkey
because Turkey is so important to the
Middle East. So I would say the best
road for Greece is the strongest
possible relations with the European
Union. That's where Greece is going to
be protected. There was a piece in the
in the newspaper just today that Erdogan
made a statement yesterday saying that
uh that he's very angry that the EU, his
words, is dragging its feet on Turkish
accession talks. We don't want Turkey in
the European Union. It's not a European
country and it's a
belligerent. Maybe when Turkish troops
withdraw from Cyprus, then we can have
that conversation. But until then, I
think Greece needs to rely on its
friends in Europe and while maintaining
good relations with the United States,
not rely on the United States for its
security. This is that's very serious.
Thank you very much. A last message to
Greeks in Greek.
[Music]
Intelligence and Security Forum.
Castillo Santoino.